Hi, welcome back to our retreat together.I
like to call it Sending the Virus to the Middle of the Sun.
It would be a beautiful thing to do.
So now we're going on with the quotations.
'JAM DPAL RTZA RGYUD LAS,
which means, Pabongka Rinpoche is going to quote a famous tantra and this is the tantra of Manjushri.
It's called what we call a root tantra,
which means it's the original tantra from which the practice of Manjushri came.
Then normally you get lots of
secondary tantras by the Buddha.
And then you get a pile of
commentaries in the Tengyur.
Then you get a bigger pile of
commentaries by Tibetan wise people.
That's normally the process.
So we're going straight back to the original of Tantra, to the beginning of Tantra.
And it says  ,TSUL KHRIMS 'CHAL LA THUB DBANG GIS,
,SNGAGS 'GRUB PAR NI MA GSUNGS TE,
,MYA NGAN LAS 'DAS GRONG 'GRO, ,MYA NGAN LAS 'DAS GRONG
Something's wrong here with the meter, small mistake
MYA NGAN LAS 'DAS GRONG 'GRO YI,
,YUL DANG PHYOGS KYANG MA YIN NO,
TSUL KHRIMS 'CHAL LA THUB DBANG GIS,
Now people who may be very serious
spiritual practitioners in the sense of
spending a lot of time in retreat  or
Learning the great books, learning Tibetan, trying to master all these things,
but if they're not nice to other people,
if they don't treat other people sweetly
,SNGAGS 'GRUB PAR NI MA GSUNGS TE,
The Buddha never said they could practice Tantra.
The Buddha never gave permission for
those people to practice the Diamond Way.
,MYA NGAN LAS 'DAS GRONG 'GRO, ,MYA NGAN LAS 'DAS GRONG
going to the city of Nirvana
,YUL DANG PHYOGS KYANG MA YIN NO,
They are not going to the right destination and
they're not even headed in the right direction. Okay?
So like if you're going from Sedona
to the major city of Rimrock and
you start heading the opposite way west, then you're headed the opposite way from from Rimrock
and you have to go around the world to get to Rimrock.
So the same for secret teachings.
If you don't treat other people sweetly then
not only you're not going to reach Rimrock,
you're going to go exactly in the wrong direction.
,BYIS PA NGAN PA 'DI LA NI,
,SNGAGS 'GRUB PA NI GA LA YOD,
,SKYE BO TSUL KHRIMS 'CHAL 'DI LA,
,DE LA BDE 'GRO GA LA YOD,
It means, he calls those people who try to
practice tantra and who don't treat other people nice,
he calls them naughty kids.
So, it's kind of, here you have Manjushri in the original Manjushri tantra saying, "Those naughty kids,
who say they're going to practice tantra,
how can they if they're not treating other people nice?"
GA LA YOD, means totally impossible.
,SKYE BO TSUL KHRIMS 'CHAL 'DI LA,
If people aren't nice to other people
,DE LA BDE 'GRO GA LA YOD,
They won't even come back to a higher rebirth.
I mean, they'll be born as an insect
or something, If they practice tantra.
,MTHO RIS SU YANG MI 'GYUR ZHING,
,BDE BA MCHOG TU'ANG MI 'GYUR NA,
They won't even come back to human birth,
much less the highest kind of happiness.
,RGYAL BAS GSUNGS PA'I SNGAGS RNAMS NI,
,'GRUB PAR 'GYUR BA SMOS CI DGOS,
Then how can these people,
who are not nice to other people,
they're trying to practice tantra,
they say they're practicing tantra and
then they hurt other people,
they're not even going to come back as a human,
they'll come back like as a grasshopper.
He said, What kind of tantra is that if you practice it and you become a grasshopper?"
It's probably not the highest teachings that I can make your Buddha in one life time.
Alright
I went and got the quotation as usual.
And it's, the full Sanskrit name of this
Manjushri Tantra is Arya Manjushri Mullah Tantra.
It has the same quotation,  MYA NGAN LAS 'DAS GRONG.
By the way our prediction of the correct pronunciation is correct, MYA NGAN LAS 'DAS GRONG.
So the Tibetan here has a mistake in the Lam Rim.
So this is the benefit of all you guys working
so hard, especially Gold Club, Jade Club,
to help support John Brady's project.
Great, great work. And because of that project,
I can easily go to the original tantra and give
you some dessert on top of this quotation.
,TA LA'I SHING GI MGO PA NI;
;GANG TSE BCAD PAR GYUR PA NA'ANG,
SNGON PO NYID KYI SKAL MED NA,
,MYU GU NAM ZHIG 'BYUNG BAR 'GYUR, ,
If you cut the top off a tree, which we're
going to show here in a picture and
it took me a while to find this picture. I had
it very clear, the words are very clear and
this is what it would look like, you know a tree cut in half.
If you cut the top off of a tree, let's say it's an apple tree or something.
He gives the example of a palm tree.
If you cut off the top,
SNGON PO NYID KYI SKAL MED NA,
how's it ever going to grow any branches?
MYU GU NAM ZHIG 'BYUNG BAR 'GYUR,
Where would the branches come out? Where would
the tender shoots of your enlightenment come out
if you chopped the top half of the tree off?
So that's an interesting example because treating other people nice,
he could do the normal thing and say, "Oh,
this is the foundation of all secret practice,
or this is the root of all secret practice,"
but he for some reason, which I guess you guys can discuss in your discussion groups,
he flips the image around.
He doesn't say you've destroyed the roots,
he said you've destroyed the
whole upper half of the fruit tree.
So, how can you expect any fruits out of it? How can you even expect any small branches to start growing?
You've destroyed your chances for
apples if you cut off the top 50% of the tree.
YANG 'GA' ZHIG GIS NGES 'BYUNG BYANG SEMS YANG DAG PA'I LTA BA GANG YANG MED PAR
Then some people they try to practice
without the three principal paths.
Those of you who have taken the ACI courses,
this is the whole subject of the first
ACI course is the three principal paths.
You can call them renunciation,
bodhichitta, and correct view.
I think It's not very friendly English.
I think the first one is I'm tired of this kind of life.
I'm tired of this kind of, I'm tired of seeing people die.
I'm tired of seeing things fall apart.
It's just to much, I'm tired of it.
That's the first one.
The second one is, and I wish nobody
else had to go through these things either.
I wish we could all become enlightened.
I wish I could do something to help
every living being in the universe.
By the way, that's the kind of attitude
that we're going to use in the meditations
to try to send the virus into the middle of the sun.
We're going to overkill.
We're going to do prayers for all
the people in the universe.
Then, you know, something as small as a
virus is definitely going to get killed by this,
prayers that are as big as the
universe and I'm speaking literally.
And then the  YANG DAG PA'I LTA BA
means just see that in the kitchen, that
the husband that you were upset at was never there.
I think those are three friendly ways to say
renunciation,  bodhichitta, correct view.
Or you could say, "I'm tired of all this and
I'm tired of seeing my friends suffer,
and it's all based on some kind of crazy belief in someone who's not even there.
I would like to fix this."
Now, he says MED PAR,
in the second line here.
Which means some people never heard of these three attitudes, these three principal paths of Buddhism,
they never got there.
SEMS NGO BSKYANGS PA'I SGOM ZHIG LA.
They try to do this kind of meditation.
it's a mistaken meditation where you watch your
mind and you don't watch it for signs of thinking
that the husband comes from his on side.
You're not watching for signs of that.
You're just watching the mind think and that's called
SEMS NGO BSKYANGS PA.
It's a meditation that's a mistaken meditation
where you sit and watch your mind think and
how long you stay at that,  MI TSE BSKYAL BA means
people waste their whole life, people
spend years staring at a wall or
trying to think that their mind is empty or something like that.
He says  BRTZON PA DON MED DU SONG.
It is completely useless effort.
BRTZON PA means effort. DON MED means
meaningless, there's no point to it.
It's like fishing in your bathtub or something,
for tuna fish or something.
It's not never going to happen.
It's not possible. It's just weird.
SONG BA STE, DES NI RAB NA MI G-YO BA'I LAS SU 'GRO TSUL SOGS
And our Lama, he went on, he went off,
probably on the lions dance,
he said,  "look, the first eight levels of
the lions dance if you just do that,
you know, all you can do is
collect a certain kind of karma that will,
it's called unshifting karma.
What do you call that? It cannot be diverted, undiverted karma and it means if you collect that karma,
normally you are born into the form realm or the formless realm. And you spend a long time there, and you waste your time and
then you go to the hell realms. So, he says, "Look it wastes your whole life and it wastes the many
lifetimes after that, and wastes many eons after that.
ThenBSKYAR BSHAD. BSKYAR BSHAD means
BCAS STZAL means then our lama wraped things up. He went to a summary. He wrapped things up and
Yay, we finished another day in the original teachings. Okay, which is a big deal.
The original teachings are 24 days total.
Pabongka Rinpoche went on for 24 days.
We're going to do something similar with this lamrim.
I mean this month.
There were 24 days total of teaching.
We started this lamrim series 10 years ago or roughly,
by doing the last two days, day 23 and day 24.
Because these are how to meditate and
how to see emptinesses. So we thought
it would be cool to start with those two and then we would do the lamrim from the beginning.
I just stopped to give you a progress report.
Now we're about to start day 16.
But really we finished two extra days.
So now we're starting day 19.
so in 19, 20, 21, 22, ...
We have six days left and we have finished
eighteen days. So we are like 70, 75 % finished.
That's pretty cool.
I guess you could say we're going to take another two years or three years or something like that.
And I promised you guys for dessert
we will go to the great lamrim of Tsongkhapa
and read his section on shamatha and vipassana,
how to go into deep meditation on emptiness.
All right
In the Tibetan ` ,,NYIN BCU DRUG PAR,
On the 16th day,
DANG POR RTZIS BZHAG GNANG BA ,
You are lucky that this custom has not spread to the west
Okay . This is called . means
Like three months before the lamrim teachings
the teacher will say, "Everybody has to
memorize the outline of the lamrim."
You can't get into the room unless you
memorize the outline of the lamrim.
My teacher used to do it with the tantric vows and
the bodhisattva vows. He would not let us in the room unless we could recite them.
(the vows in Tibetan)
I still remember them, so I guess it was useful.
So, it's accustom to make the students memorize the outline and
the teacher
also has to memorize it. The teacher would close their eyes and they will sing it from memory and
then the student, the whole audience will sing it back. It's a very nice custom. It's a very beautiful custom.
So our lama on the 16th day, Pabongka Rinpoche,  he did  about the outline
PHYAG BZHES LTAR
He kept to the old system. He kept the old custom of
starting his teaching the old way, which is the good way.
Then he said,
JI SKAD DU, KHAMS GSUM CHOS KYI RGYAL PO TZONG KHA PA CHEN PO'I ZHAL NAS,
NGES 'BYUNG DE YANG RNAM DAG SEMS BSKYED KYIS ,ZHES SOGS 'DREN PAR 289B MDZAD
NGES 'BYUNG DE YANG RNAM DAG SEMS (not complete)
And he quoted
the Three Principal Paths actually
by Je Tsongkapa, and he quoted a special section and
it says,
"Ok, maybe you are,
maybe you finally reached a point in your life where you are scared of life or you are
worried about life or you are tired of life,
you know, you wish could be better." And I think the virus is helping us all to get there.
Maybe you have got to the first principal path now. Well, then you have to wrap it in
bodhichitta. You have to wrap it in the wish that you could help other people reach their own freedom. Okay.
So that's, he's quoting,
to start the class, to start the day,
the lama, after they did
they will quote a famous piece of Scripture, which is going to apply to the teaching of the day.
ZHES SOGS 'DREN PAR 289B MDZAD NAS NGES 'BYUNG GI STENG DU BYANG SEMS DGOS TSUL
He repeated to us how we had to take
this first principal path,
"I'm tired of all this trouble in life and you have to wrap it in bodhichitta." Okay?
BRTZAMS PA'I SNGON 'GRO KUN SLONG 'CHOS TSUL
And he encouraged us to
KUN SLONG 'CHOS
to examine our heart,
decide why are we here, why are we studying lamrim? And it's to help other people.
When you help other people, you're also helping yourself, so
focus on other people during the time of the virus
don't worry about helping yourself, help other people and then you yourself will get helped by the way.
If you send the virus into the sun, if you do prayers for all living beings in the universe,
you will cover the virus don't worry. All right, and I have a picture here of a bunch of puppies
in a group,
because I distinctly remember
asking this question to my teacher.
We were in the kitchen, the famous kitchen at this Mongolian temple and I
was studying Lam.
In fact, it's the first book I ever translated. It's a version of Maitreya's
outline of the five,
the three sets of five paths each, 15 paths and
I asked my teacher, you know, that the sign of
reaching the first path
is renunciation.
It's being tired of this life, but
when you get to the
bodhisattva path, the five paths for a bodhisattva, mahayana level,
the first path is different, the first path is
is working to help all living beings, you know. So I said,
"That's a little confusing to me, you know."
In DCI terms a
tragedy in your life will get you started. Then I  said, "Rinpoche, why is that tragedy called
reaching bodhichitta in the higher teachings, for the Mahayana track." and he said, "Think about it,
it's still the tragedy, it's just a universal tragedy, it's a tragedy
involving
every single being in this universe, that's a big tragedy." So I'd like to call it Rinpoche's answer.
Or you could say a puppy in a group. I kind of like that idea.
You're not worried about one puppy you're worried about the whole basket of puppies,
which is the universe.
SA BCAD SONG ZIN PA RNAMS JI LTAR SONG TSUL DANG,
SA BCAD you know if you've been taking these classes.
Our lama reviewed the outline to show us
where we were and we're going to do that shortly.
THAR PAR BGROD PA'I LAM GYI RANG BZHIN GTAN LA DBAB PA NAS BSKYAR BSHAD MDZAD,
He went over the steps to the path to Nirvana, personal Nirvana again.
He briefly went over them. Mainly the three trainings, right, and the wheel of life.
Then, the lama's getting warmed up. The audience is getting warmed up. I think these lamas do these introductions because
when you have a few thousand yak herders to get into a room,
they're probably always late. There's no clocks in the whole country. So the lamas cover some other stuff for a while.
RANG RE 'KHOR BAR GANG GIS 'KHOR NA LAS KYIS 'KHOR LA,
So what makes me
keep doing the same thing over and over. Why do I keep going in these huge cycles in my life?
I meet somebody, we have a relationship, it gets old, we break off,
you know, I'm sad for a while,
then I meet a new person and then, why do I go through these big cycles ?
'KHOR NA LAS LAS KYIS 'KHOR
Karma's forcing you in those huge circles.
DE YANG NYON MONGS KYIS BSKYED,
What triggers that karma is my negative emotions.
NYON MONGS PA'I NANG NAS KYANG RTZA BA MA RIG PA
And what triggers all the negative emotions,
I think the husband is coming from his own side,
that's what triggers it.
BSKYED PA NYID
that's it and nothing else.
You can't point to any other reason for our pain
then thinking that things come from their own side.
DE RTZAD NAS GCOD PA LA LHAG PA SHES RAB KYI BSLAB PA BSKYED DGOS
If you want to tear out
the root of
the of the unhappiness you're experiencing in this life
you must tear out the idea that things are coming this way, that things are coming from their side.
Yeah.
DE BSKYED PA LA TING NGE 'DZIN DANG TSUL KHRIMS KYI BSLAB PA SNGON DU 'GRO DGOS
If you really want to tear out
this deep-seated belief that the world is coming this way,
then you're going to need two things. Number one. You have to learn to meditate
you have to be meditating every day and to meditate you need
What?
For ten dollars?
Huh?
Say it again. Morality
Both actually, yeah, but here's where he ties,
he ties
Yeah, because he's working backwards in a chain of causality, right? And now he has reached
if you want wisdom you need meditation. If you want meditation, you need to treat other people nice. Otherwise if you upset other people's
minds, how you ever going to sit down and have your mind be peaceful,
That's not karma?
TSUL KHRIMS KYI BSLAB PA SNGON DU 'GRO DGOS PA'I PHYIR TSUL KHRIMS NI
Therefore the foundation of everything is
TSUL KHRIMS, is treating other people well.
YON TAN GYI GZHI MA Okay.
Sometimes the word GZHI which means foundation, has a MA on it,
because the word MA in Tibetan, although it can mean negative. It also means mom.
Sometimes they glue it onto the word for foundation to say like the mother, the mother foundation or something.
So some people translate this negative and they'll get in trouble. It's not MA YIN, it's GZHI MA, YIN.
So, okay, YIN TSUL DANG.
Alright, and then lastly,
Pabongka Rinpoche closes
this section
masterfully with
An unbelievable image. Okay. So I'm going to show you an image here of two guys,
two guys getting to know each other. You know somebody
introduced somebody else to somebody at the office,
and you know, the guy says
"Meet my friend so-and-so he has a business proposal for you." And the other guys like, Yeah
tell me what it's about."
There's a song called Getting to Know You and
it's like I didn't know you very well
and then I tried to get to know you and
now I got to know you and now I love, I actually
kind of like you. So it's called Getting to Know You.
NYON MONGS PA'I GNYEN PO BSTEN SKABS,
When you are trying to apply the antidote to your negative emotions
This BSTEN means applying an antidoteBISTEN.
DANG PO NYON MONGS PA SKYER BCUG
He says, he's very funny,
Pabongka Rinpoche says, "I'll teach you a trick, Okay?"
I can see him leaning over, and don't forget he's talking to a couple of thousand people without a microphone
for like eight hours
Like unbelievable and I can just see him leaning over and sotto, sotto voice?
He's like, "I'll tell you a secret."
"What, what's the secret?" He says, "I'll teach you how to get rid of your bad habits
Bad mental habits." "Okay, teach me." You know, he says, "Okay."
DANG PO NYON MONGS PA SKYER BCUG
Let's say you have a problem with anger towards somebody like someone has been upsetting you. Okay, So you're not angry. You're not throwing,
you're not throwing things all day.
I had recently a couple call me and they said we're
at the throwing stage.
We're starting to throw things at each other
I said, okay, we have to, we have to
cover this second husband thing.
Okay
DANG PO NYON MONGS PA SKYER BCUG
So when you're sitting by yourself
and you're calm and
you know, you're kind of mildly happy,
if you're at the throwing stage with your partner,
you know, tossing things at each other,
They weren't throwing things at each
other, they were throwing garbage cans
on the floor and stuff.
So anyway, NYON MONGS PA SKYER BCUG
Close your eyes and try to recreate the situation.
So close your eyes and
this person comes into your room and
they start saying something which really, really hurts you. Really hurts your heart, you know, and try to recreate
this situation while you're calm and you're sitting on the couch and
close your eyes and imagine your husband comes in and starts accusing you of something or something like that.
Just do that. SKYER BCUG means
see if you can get to that emotion
artificially.
See if you can get yourself upset just thinking about your husband. That's kind of a funny,
it's an amazing trick. Okay?
DE NAS NYON MONGS
Then you'll get upset, you know, you'll feel upset, then open your eyes real quick
and try to catch how it feels to be upset. Okay?
Like try to catch the feeling.
NGOS ZIN
NGOS ZIN means learn to recognize how it feels to start to get upset
by practicing getting upset, by thinking about the bad things your husband said to you in the past.
It's very amazing method, you know. We should have put it in the meditations Tim, maybe you guys can do it in the groups
Get used to identifying
how it feels to start to get upset
in your own heart. Okay,
by doing upset meditations. That's so cool.
SKYER BCUG GNYEN PO BSTEN
And then practice applying the antidote.
"Oh, oh he's not coming from his side. He's coming
from me. When he says those things to me
that's coming from me.
I have to remembered that, I have to remember,"
YENGS NA'ANG NGOS ZIN PA'I GNAD YOD
Then he makes a funny,
he says, he's so funny. He says,
"Look it's going to mess up your whole day.
YENGS NA'ANG means it's going to mess up your whole day.
NGOS ZIN PA'I GNAD
This is the marma, what do you it call it? Marma hata.
The killing point, but there's a GNAD, GNAD here means,
yeah, it's gonna throw your whole day off balance
to do this meditation where you practice getting upset
at your husband, but
NGOS ZIN PA'I GNAD
the crucial point of this mini meditation is to
learn to identify
how it feels to be upset, so when you start
to get upset you can stop yourself.
YOD TSUL SOGS GSUNGS,
That's how our teacher wrapped up
the morning's comments.
And that's how we're wrapping up this episode.
So thank you for coming to Lam Rim.
Don't forget to practice this upset meditation,
if you're lucky your husband will just come in the room and help you and
you know, it actually works pretty well.
By the way, we're not trying to identify
what it feels like to be upset, we all know that, okay. We're trying to learn to recognize
What it feels to start to get upset.
Because that's where you can stop it. Once you're upset. It's almost impossible to stop.
So, if we could learn to recognize
the first few minutes of being upset,
then we could do something about it.
We could apply wisdom. Okay.
All right, cool
See you then in episode number nine.